>> ANNOUNCER: Thank you to our sponsors.
Gracias a nuestros patrocinadores.
Platinum Sponsor: Gravity Forms.
Patrocinador Platino: Gravity Forms.
Build accessible, powerful WordPress forms with Gravity Forms.
Crea formularios accesibles y potentes para WordPress con Gravity Forms,
Flexible tools for creators, developers, and teams of all sizes.
herramientas flexibles para creadores, desarrolladores y equipos de todos los tamaños.
Platinum Sponsor: WP Engine.
Patrocinador Platino: WP Engine.
WP Engine provides the most relied-upon
WP Engine proporciona los más confiables
and trusted WordPress products for businesses,
productos de WordPress para empresas,
brands, and agencies of all sizes.
marcas y agencias de todos los tamaños.
Platinum Sponsor: Woo.
Patrocinador latino: Woo.
WooCommerce is the open source
WooCommerce es de código abierto
e-commerce platform built on WordPress,
plataforma de comercio electrónico construida en WordPress,
helping merchants worldwide sell,
ayudando a comerciantes de todo el mundo a vender,
manage, and grow their businesses.
gestionar y hacer crecer sus negocios.
Gold Sponsors: Ally – Web Accessibility,
Patrocinadores Oro: Ally Web Accessibility,
Equalize Digital – websites for everyone,
Equalize Digital – sitios web para todos,
GoDaddy, GreenGeeks Web Hosting, Yoast.
GoDaddy, alojamiento web GreenGeeks, Yoast.
Silver Sponsors: AAArdvark, CodeGeek,
Patrocinadores Plata: AAArdvark,
Kinetic Iris, Kinsta, Pressable, Second Melody.
Kinetic Iris, Kinsta, Pressable, Second Melody.
Bronze Sponsors: 9 Planets Hosting,
Patrocinadores Bronce: 9 Planets Hosting,
Engage, Draw Attention, Multidots,
Engage, Draw Attention, MultiDots,
NerdPress, OSOM Studio, OZeWAI – Australian
NerdPress, Osom Studio,
Progress Planner, QualityLogic,
Progress Planner, QualityLogic,
Sharp, Simply Schedule Appointments, SiteGround, StellarWP,
Sharp, Simply Schedule Appointments, SiteGround, StellarWP,
Termageddon, WebYes.
Termageddon, WebYes.
>> ALICIA ST. ROSE: Welcome to WordPress Accessibility Day 2025.
Bienvenidos a WordPress Día de la Accesibilidad 2025.
My name is Alicia St. Rose from WP with Heart.
Mi nombre es Alicia St. Rose de WP With Heart.
Thank you for joining us
Gracias por acompañarnos
for Auslan Accessibility in WordPress, Themes,
en Accesibilidad de Auslan en WordPress, temas
and Plugins for the Whole Deaf Australian Community,
y plugins para toda la comunidad sorda australiana,
with Shawn Phua.
con Shawn Phua.
Shawn is a profoundly Deaf Asian-Australian man
Shawn es un hombre asiático-australiano sordo
in his 30s who has lived in Meanjin,
de unos 30 años que ha vivido en Meanjin,
Brisbane, Australia, for most of his life.
también conocida como Brisbane, Australia, durante la mayor parte de su vida.
He is fluent in Auslan and English and does
Se comunica con fluidez en Auslan y en inglés y no
not lip-read or speak.
lee los labios ni habla.
Shawn was born to Malaysian-Chinese-hearing parents
Shawn nació de padres oyentes de origen chino-malasio
in a multilingual family where English is their fourth language
en una familia multilingüe donde el inglés es su cuarto idioma
after Cantonese, Malay, Bahasa Malaysia, and Mandarin.
después del cantonés, malayo/bahasa malayo y mandarín.
Shawn and his parents communicate
Shawn y sus padres se comunican
in a mixture of signs from Auslan,
en una mezcla de señas Auslan,
Australian Signed English, Malaysian Sign Language,
Inglés de señas australiano, lengua de señas de Malasia,
and Singaporean Sign Language at home.
y lengua de señas de Singapur en casa.
Shawn has experience in teaching and tutoring,
Shawn tiene experiencia en enseñanza y tutoría,
and supporting a wide range of people,
y apoyando a una amplia gama de personas,
including families of Deaf children,
incluidas familias de niños sordos,
hearing Auslan students, participants
estudiantes y participantes de Auslan
from National Disability Insurance schemes,
del Plan Nacional de Seguro de Discapacidad,
and migrants, refugees, adults,
y migrantes, refugiados, adultos,
and seniors from various communities.
y personas mayores de diversas comunidades.
He holds multiple screening checks
Realiza múltiples evaluaciones
and Working with Children cards
y trabaja con tarjetas para niños
across different Australian states and territories.
en diferentes estados australianos y territorios.
Shawn enjoys collecting resources about different sign languages,
A Shawn le gusta coleccionar recursos sobre diferentes lenguas de señas,
such as dictionaries, books, posters, and flyers.
como diccionarios, libros, carteles y folletos.
He also likes learning signs, alphabets,
También le gusta aprender señas, alfabetos
and numbers from other sign languages, especially when he meets
y números de otras lenguas de señas,
Deaf visitors from other countries
especialmente cuando se encuentra con visitantes sordos de otros países
or Deaf First Nations Australians,
o sordos australianos de las Primeras Naciones,
migrants, and refugees in Australia.
migrantes y refugiados en Australia.
Please feel free to ask your questions
Por favor, siéntete libre de hacer tus preguntas
in the Zoom Q&A section,
en la sección de preguntas y respuestas de Zoom,
and we'll answer them at the end of this session.
y las responderemos al final de esta sesión.
Also, don't forget to use the chat to connect
Además, no olvides usar el chat para conectarte
with other attendees.
con otros asistentes.
>> SHAWN PHUA: Hello, everyone.
Hola a todos.
My name is Shawn Phua,
Mi nombre es Shawn Phua,
and I am completely Deaf.
y soy completamente sordo.
My preferred pronouns
Mis pronombres preferidos
are he, him, and his.
son él y suyo.
I'm very excited to present today
Estoy muy emocionado de presentar hoy
for about 30 minutes about
durante unos 30 minutos aproximadamente
Auslan Accessibility in WordPress Themes,
la accesibilidad de Auslan en temas de WordPress,
and all of the things that incorporate
y todo lo relacionado con la incorporación de
the Deaf community and involve them in Australia.
la comunidad sorda y su participación en Australia.
I know this is an international audience.
Sé que esta es una audiencia internacional.
However, I'm from Australia, and I also have captioning enabled.
Sin embargo, soy de Australia y también tengo subtítulos habilitados.
The overall goal is to educate people and ensure
El objetivo general es educar a las personas y garantizar
that things like WordPress and websites
que cosas como WordPress y sitios web
are completely accessible, culturally appropriate,
sean completamente accesibles, culturalmente apropiados
and affirming for the Australian Deaf community,
y afirmativos para la comunidad sorda australiana,
where Auslan is visible, respected,
donde Auslan sea visible, respetado
and integrated into digital experiences.
e integrado en las experiencias digitales.
As I mentioned, I'm Shawn, and Auslanism
Como ya mencioné, soy Shawn y Auslanism
is my business, my small business.
es mi negocio, mi pequeño negocio.
I live in Australia, in Brisbane, Queensland.
Vivo en Australia, en Brisbane, Queensland.
First of all, "How to get a Deaf person's attention?"
Primero: “¿Cómo llamar la atención de una persona sorda?”
A gentle tap on the shoulder or on the upper arm
Un toque suave en el hombro o en la parte superior del brazo
is quite respectful to Deaf culture.
es bastante respetuoso dentro de la cultura sorda.
This slide is about Deaf people being able
Esta diapositiva trata sobre que las personas sordas pueden
to do anything except hear.
hacer cualquier cosa excepto oír.
What we do is hear through our eyes.
Nosotros escuchamos a través de los ojos.
You may wonder what the Auslan alphabet,
Quizá te preguntes ¿qué es el alfabeto Auslan?
fingerspelt alphabet, looks like.
Parece un alfabeto escrito con los dedos.
This is just a small example.
Este es solo un pequeño ejemplo.
In Australia, an Australian sign language known
En Australia, la lengua de señas australiana conocida
as "Auslan" uses a two-hand fingerspelling method.
como “Auslan” utiliza un método de deletreo manual a dos manos.
For example, in America,
Por ejemplo, en Estados Unidos,
they use a one-handed fingerspelling method
usan un método de deletreo manual a una mano
through ASL, American Sign Language,
a través del ASL, lengua de señas americana,
and in international sign language,
y la lengua de señas internacional,
used by the World Federation of the Deaf,
utilizada por la Federación Mundial de Sordos,
for Deaf people, uses a one-handed sign language
que también emplea un sistema a una mano distinto del ASL.
which is different to ASL.
En Australia, las personas sordas
In Australia, Deaf people sign a little differently.
firman de un poco diferente.
They might sign "B"
Por ejemplo, la “B”
in two different ways, "P" or "S,"
puede firmarse de dos maneras, como “P” o “S”,
just as people might pronounce different words
así como las personas pronuncian palabras de forma distinta
in a different accent.
según el acento.
We all have slight differences.
Todos tenemos pequeñas diferencias.
An interesting fact is, the Australian fingerspelt alphabet
Un dato interesante es que el alfabeto australiano escrito con los dedos
originated from British Sign Language,
se originó del lenguaje de señas británico,
going back when Australia was colonized.
desde la época de la colonización de Australia.
BSL has its own sign language,
El BSL tiene su propia lengua de señas
and it also uses a two-handed fingerspelling,
y también utiliza un deletreo manual a dos manos,
which is very similar to Auslan.
muy similar al Auslan.
Auslan Video Integration.
Integración de video en Auslan.
You might be thinking about how WordPress
Quizá estés pensando cómo WordPress,
and the internet, and websites,
internet y los sitios web
can be accessible to the Deaf community.
pueden ser accesibles para la comunidad sorda.
These points on the PowerPoint outline some suggestions
Estos puntos de la presentación de PowerPoint describen algunas sugerencias
for integrating Auslan translations.
para integrar traducciones en Auslan.
Using English text as well,
Utilizando también texto en inglés,
either above or below the information,
ya sea arriba o debajo de la información,
can assist Deaf people to understand
puede ayudar a las personas sordas a comprender
information in their preferred language
la información en su idioma preferido
and make it easy English, simplified English,
y facilitar el inglés, en inglés sencillo,
rather than using too much jargon
en lugar de usar demasiada jerga
and highfalutin words, because Deaf people
y palabras complejas, porque a las personas sordas
might find that difficult to follow.
puede resultarles difícil seguirlo.
Using accessible videos,
Usar videos accesibles,
using things like players,
utilizando reproductores como
AblePlayer, Video.js, or WordPress-compatible plugins.
Able Player, Video.js o plugins compatibles con WordPress.
That will support transcripts and easy playback controls,
Esto permitirá transcripciones y controles de reproducción sencillos,
which makes it much easier for Deaf people to navigate.
lo que facilita mucho la navegación para personas sordas.
Try to provide short video explainers for key pages
Intenta proporcionar videos explicativos cortos para páginas clave
such as the homepage, the contact page,
como la página de inicio, la página de contacto
and particular forms that might be integrated.
y formularios específicos que puedan integrarse.
Otherwise, things can be quite complicated
De lo contrario, las cosas pueden resultar
and difficult to navigate.
bastante complicadas y difíciles de navegar.
Fourthly, using picture-in-picture split screen layouts,
En cuarto lugar, usar diseños de pantalla dividida o imagen en imagen,
having things side by side.
tener los elementos lado a lado
If there's a presenter,
si hay un presentador,
trying to put the Deaf interpreter or the translator,
intentando colocar al intérprete o traductor sordo
whether they be a hearing-translator/interpreter
ya sea un intérprete oyente o un intérprete sordo,
or Deaf interpreter, side by side,
uno junto al otro,
so it's very visually easy to glean
para que la información sea visualmente fácil de entender
the information by the audience,
para la audiencia.
and it's easy to navigate as well.
Y también facilita la navegación.
On my laptop, whether I use a computer or an iPad,
En mi computadora portátil, ya sea que use una computadora o un iPad,
I make sure that the audience can see me today,
me aseguro de que la audiencia pueda verme hoy,
even though my laptop is different
aunque mi portátil sea diferente
to what you're seeing on the screen.
a lo que estás viendo en pantalla.
Deaf people and hearing people
Personas sordas y oyentes
might be interpreters, but we need to make sure
pueden ser intérpretes, pero debemos asegurarnos
that they are framed correctly so that it's very easy to understand
de que estén correctamente encuadrados para que sea fácil comprender
the sign language, and the hands are not cut off.
la lengua de señas y que las manos no queden cortadas.
There are particular themes
Hay temas específicos
that are accessible and plugins.
y plugins accesibles.
You would need to select WordPress themes
Necesitarás seleccionar temas de WordPress
that are compatible
que sean compatibles
to (WCAG) 2.1 so they're compliant
con WCAG 2.1
and they support the embedded media without breaking the design,
y que soporten contenido multimedia integrado sin romper el diseño,
because if that design is broken,
porque si el diseño se rompe,
Deaf people will decide perhaps not to engage.
las personas sordas podrían decidir no interactuar.
We want Deaf people to engage in all of your websites,
Queremos que las personas sordas participen en todos sus sitios web,
so it's important to have that design element
por lo que es importante tener una buena estructura de diseño
and navigational elements.
y navegación.
Navigation is really important for Deaf people.
La navegación es realmente importante para las personas sordas.
Also, using plugins in your design.
Además, utiliza plugins en tu diseño.
Using the "Accessibility Widget"
Usa el “Accessibility Widget”
or the "Accessible Video Gallery,"
o “Accessible Video Gallery”,
which ensures that videos and the navigation is compatible
que garantizan que los videos y la navegación sean compatibles
with screenreaders and also with keyboard controls.
con lectores de pantalla y controles de teclado.
There are some Deaf people
Hay algunas personas sordas
who are also visually impaired or blind, and so they use
que también tienen discapacidad visual o son ciegas, y por eso utilizan
those particular elements to read scripts
estos elementos para leer guiones
through English texts or transcripts.
a través de textos o transcripciones en inglés.
There are also Deaf people who might not use sign language
También hay personas sordas que pueden no usar lengua de señas
and rely on the written word and audio descriptions as well.
y dependen de la palabra escrita y también de descripciones de audio.
When I'm signing in Auslan,
Cuando firmo en Auslan,
having my video as I'm signing enables people
tener mi video mientras firmo permite a las personas
to actually see who I am,
ver realmente quién soy,
and having an audio description can explain what I look like,
y una descripción de audio puede explicar cómo luzco.
so it's really good to include
Por eso es muy bueno incluir
every element and the plugins as well that allow
todos esos elementos y plugins, así como opciones de
the toggling and the different features.
alternar diferentes funciones.
For example, showing an Auslan video means
Por ejemplo, mostrar un video en Auslan significa
that the Deaf Australian community can follow along.
que la comunidad sorda australiana pueda seguirlo.
Information is accessible.
La información se vuelve accesible.
Somebody who might be hard
Alguien con pérdida auditiva
of hearing might need to select "closed captioning"
podría necesitar seleccionar “subtítulos”
to access the information.
para acceder a la información.
It would be different depending upon what type
Esto variará según el tipo
of Deafness the person has,
de sordera de la persona,
and remembering that your audience will be varied,
y recuerda que tu audiencia será diversa:
there would be signing Deaf people,
personas sordas que usan señas,
Deaf people who don't sign,
personas sordas que no utilizan señas,
hard-of-hearing people,
personas con problemas de aludición,
and Deafblind people.
y personas sordociegas.
Deaf people also might have additional disabilities
Las personas sordas también pueden tener discapacidades adicionales
and different needs,
y distintas necesidades,
so ensuring that your plugins will support and respond
así que asegúrate de que tus plugins se adapten y respondan
to the design that's required.
al diseño requerido.
Auslan videos can also be viewed on tablets as well as iPhones,
Los videos en Auslan también pueden verse en tabletas y iPhone,
different types of devices.
en distintos dispositivos.
On the slide here, there's some examples
En esta diapositiva hay algunos ejemplos
where the British Deaf community
de la comunidad sorda británica.
in the UK, the company called Signly,
En el Reino Unido, una empresa llamada Signly
has really good design elements.
tiene elementos de diseño muy buenos.
They use sign language on top of the screen
Utilizan lengua de señas en la parte superior de la pantalla.
that's being displayed.
Que se está mostrando.
They use very advanced technologies,
Utilizan tecnologías muy avanzadas,
so they might be worth Googling after my presentation.
por lo que puede valer la pena buscarlo en Google después de mi presentación.
For Deaf people that struggle with English literacy,
Para personas sordas con dificultades de alfabetización en inglés,
it's much more friendly in terms
es mucho más amigable
of access for Deaf people to be more independent,
en términos de acceso para personas sordas, permitiendo mayor independencia
not relying on family and friends to get information.
sin depender de familia o amigos para obtener información.
Having that type of design means
Este tipo de diseño permite
that the person can highlight a sentence on the screen,
que la persona resalte una frase en la pantalla,
and Signly will translate
y Signly la traducirá
that into British Sign Language via video.
a lengua de señas británica mediante video.
This technology is patented by Signly,
Esta tecnología está patentada por Signly,
and it is used, now, more and more.
y ahora se utiliza cada vez más.
It's BSL, "British Sign Language."
Es BSL, lengua de señas británica.
It can also be used for American Sign Language
También puede utilizarse para la lengua de señas americana
and South African Sign Language.
y la lengua de señas sudafricana.
Australia is still negotiating with Signly to try
Australia todavía está negociando con Signly para probar
and use this technology in our country,
y usar esta tecnología en nuestro país,
but we are a little disadvantaged because of the cost,
pero estamos un poco en desventaja debido al costo,
and we need to make sure
y debemos asegurarnos
that the Australian government legislation
de que la legislación gubernamental australiana
for equal access and disability access is compliant
sobre igualdad y acceso a la discapacidad sea compatible
with what's happening in the UK and the British legislation.
con lo que sucede en el Reino Unido y su legislación.
At the moment, we're a little behind that--
En este momento estamos un poco atrasados…
British Sign Language, because it's in their legislation,
Como la lengua de señas británica está incluida en su legislación,
they're getting more access.
ellos tienen mayor acceso.
Something interesting to think about.
Es algo interesante para reflexionar.
Next, I'd like to talk about User-Friendly Navigation,
A continuación, me gustaría hablar sobre la navegación fácil de usar,
and there are a few points up on this PowerPoint.
y hay algunos puntos arriba en esta presentación de PowerPoint.
Using a simple menu and structure
Usar un menú y una estructura simples
that is clearly labeled,
claramente etiquetados,
and avoiding, as I mentioned before, too much jargon.
y evitar, como mencioné antes, demasiada jerga.
Deaf people may not understand the jargon,
Las personas sordas pueden no entender la jerga,
so making it simple and direct.
así que mantenlo simple y directo.
It doesn't only benefit Deaf people well,
No solo beneficia a las personas sordas,
but it will benefit people who speak
también ayudará a personas que hablan
a language other than English.
otro idioma distinto del inglés.
Everyday English is much more accessible,
El inglés cotidiano es mucho más accesible
rather than something that's too highfalutin,
que algo demasiado técnico o pretencioso.
so making sure that icons are visible
Asegúrate de que los íconos sean visibles
and having icons alongside text,
y colócalos junto al texto,
which will depend on your design,
dependiendo de tu diseño,
and just keeping it in mind is a good thing.
y simplemente tenerlo en cuenta siempre es buena idea.
Also, creating dedicated Auslan resources
Además, crea espacios dedicados a recursos en Auslan
for sections in the website,
dentro de las secciones del sitio web,
for easy access to videos and translations
para facilitar el acceso a videos y traducciones
in Auslan or in sign language, so Deaf people can then use
en Auslan o lengua de señas, de modo que las personas sordas puedan usar
their preferred language to glean information.
su idioma preferido para obtener información.
Ensure that search bars are prominent
Asegúrate de que la barra de búsqueda sea visible
and allow for easy keyword access to Auslan content,
y permita introducir palabras clave fácilmente para acceder al contenido en Auslan,
because a lot of government websites or organizations
porque muchos sitios web gubernamentales u organizacionales
in Australia have Auslan videos,
en Australia tienen videos en Auslan,
but people find it very difficult to find them on the website.
pero a la gente le resulta difícil encontrarlos en el sitio.
Having inclusive design practices,
Adoptar prácticas de diseño inclusivas.
and there are a number of points, up on this slide.
Hay varios puntos en esta diapositiva.
Treating Auslan as a language that's equal
Tratar el Auslan como un idioma igual al inglés,
to English by not providing it as an add-on,
no como complemento,
but as core content.
sino como contenido principal.
Making sure that all information is accessible
Asegurarse de que toda la información sea accesible
on an equal basis to that that's provided in English.
en igualdad de condiciones que la ofrecida en inglés.
Using culturally respectful imagery,
Usar imágenes culturalmente respetuosas,
so videos of Deaf people who have lived experience,
por ejemplo videos de personas sordas con experiencia vivida,
not always hearing Auslan interpreters.
no siempre intérpretes oyentes de Auslan.
Having those things displayed is really important.
Mostrar estos elementos es muy importante.
Having color contrast, so large text options,
Tener buen contraste de color, opciones de texto grande
and easy-to-read layouts.
y diseños fáciles de leer.
Especially for users who have additional needs,
Especialmente para usuarios con necesidades adicionales,
such as visual, sight impairments,
como discapacidad visual
or maybe neurodiversity,
o neurodiversidad,
because bright colors sometimes can create headaches
porque los colores brillantes a veces provocan dolor de cabeza.
for those people, so being flexible.
Para estas personas es importante ser flexibles.
Offering content in multiple formats,
Ofrecer contenido en múltiples formatos:
as I said, in Auslan or sign language video format, English text,
video en Auslan, video en inglés, texto en inglés
and Easy English summaries.
y resúmenes en inglés sencillo.
Once you get the hang of it, it becomes quite easy.
Una vez que le tomas práctica, se vuelve bastante fácil.
Collaboration and Training.
Colaboración y capacitación.
On this slide, there are four points.
En esta diapositiva hay cuatro puntos,
It's good, just as a reminder,
solo como recordatorio:
to have Deaf people as consultants,
incluir a personas sordas como consultores,
Auslan interpreters, community organizations,
intérpretes de Auslan y organizaciones comunitarias
through the design and testing stages.
durante las etapas de diseño y pruebas.
Provide training for WordPress developers
Proporcionar capacitación para desarrolladores de WordPress
on Auslan-accessibility best practices.
sobre buenas prácticas de accesibilidad en Auslan.
Having a Deaf person
Contar con una persona sorda
there is really important because Deaf people
es realmente importante porque
can explain the cultural elements
puede explicar los elementos culturales
and the community needs for access,
y las necesidades de acceso de la comunidad,
which might not be readily understood by people who don't come
que podrían no ser fáciles de entender para quienes no pertenecen
from the community.
a la comunidad.
Having that lived experience
Tener esa experiencia vivida
is really valuable as part of the team.
es realmente valioso como parte del equipo.
Trying to establish guidelines for content creators,
Intentar establecer pautas para creadores de contenido,
such as how to develop a script in Auslan,
por ejemplo, cómo desarrollar un guion en Auslan,
to record videos with Deaf presenters,
para grabar videos con presentadores sordos,
and lastly, hosting regular feedback sessions with Deaf users.
y finalmente ofrecer sesiones periódicas de retroalimentación con usuarios sordos.
That can ensure that continuous development can occur.
Esto garantiza que el desarrollo continuo pueda realizarse.
This slide talks about the Deaf community.
Esta diapositiva habla sobre la comunidad sorda.
Often, people wonder, "What is the Deaf community,
A menudo la gente pregunta: “¿Qué es la comunidad sorda,
particularly in Australia?"
especialmente en Australia?”
Well, Auslan is short for "Australian Sign Language."
Auslan es la abreviatura de “Lengua de Señas Australiana”.
It's its own language with its own structure.
Es su propio idioma con estructura propia.
It's very rich.
Es muy rico,
It has a history, and it's a visual language.
tiene historia y es un idioma visual.
Deaf people use this
Las personas sordas lo usan
because we have visual requirements.
porque tenemos necesidades visuales de comunicación.
A lot of Deaf people are language-deprived
Muchas personas sordas sufren privación lingüística
because of education.
debido a la educación.
They may have grown up
Pueden haber crecido
with very limited signing or even signed English.
con señas muy limitadas o incluso con inglés signado.
It's not until they socialize with other Deaf people
No es hasta que socializan con otras personas sordas
that they start to learn Auslan, which is a visual language,
que comienzan a aprender Auslan, un idioma visual,
and can understand language and communication with intent.
y pueden comprender el lenguaje y comunicarse con intención.
The Deaf identity in Australia and Deaf culture
La identidad y cultura sorda en Australia
in Australia is very similar
es muy similar
to Deaf culture internationally, identity,
a la cultura sorda a nivel internacional:
and who somebody is and how they identify.
quién es cada persona y cómo se identifica.
Whether they consider themselves
Pueden considerarse
culturally Deaf, as users of sign language.
culturalmente sordos, como usuarios de lengua de señas.
They could be signing, but they might be hard
Pueden usar señas, o tener pérdida auditiva
of hearing or have lost their hearing later in life.
adquirida más tarde en la vida.
They might be what we would say "oral Deaf people"
También pueden ser personas sordas orales,
who learn to lip-read and speak.
que aprenden a leer labios y hablar.
Some people change their identity over time as they learn to sign,
Algunas personas cambian su identidad con el tiempo al aprender señas,
and become what we say is capital "D" Deaf and are proud of being part
y pasan a ser “Sordos” con D mayúscula, orgullosos de formar parte
of the Deaf community.
de la comunidad sorda.
Some people have lost their hearing
Algunas personas pierden la audición
and do not identify as culturally Deaf,
y no se identifican como culturalmente sordas,
using speech, still, and technology to communicate.
siguen usando el habla y tecnología para comunicarse.
They might call themselves "hard of hearing."
Pueden llamarse "con problemas de audición ".
It's important to have eye contact
Es importante mantener contacto visual
with a person when you are communicating with them,
cuando te comunicas con alguien,
making sure that you can enunciate
asegurarte de articular
your words clearly if they are lip-reading,
tus palabras claramente si la persona lee los labios,
and being able to nod to show your understanding.
y asentir para mostrar que comprendes.
As I mentioned before, tapping on the shoulder gently to get
Como mencioné antes, tocar suavemente el hombro para llamar
somebody's attention if they're facing you, or not,
la atención de alguien, esté o no frente a ti,
maybe get in front of their line of sight
o colocarte dentro de su campo visual
so that you can actually get their attention,
para que pueda verte,
but not coming too close.
pero sin acercarte demasiado,
That can be considered rude, and making sure
ya que puede considerarse descortés.
that lighting is clear so that you can see
También asegúrate de que la iluminación sea adecuada
each other and it's not distracting.
para poder verse mutuamente sin distracciones.
Making sure that you get to the point.
Ir directo al punto.
Deaf people like it when you get to the point
A las personas sordas les gusta cuando eres directo
and not beat around the bush.
y no das rodeos.
Also, respect for Deaf elders
También respetar a las personas sordas mayores
and the history of the Deaf community.
y la historia de la comunidad sorda.
There are challenges, however, in accessing interpreters
Sin embargo, existen desafíos: acceso a intérpretes,
and accessing live captioning and other communication supports.
subtítulos en vivo y otros apoyos de comunicación.
There are interpreter shortages, there's a high demand,
Hay escasez de intérpretes, gran demanda
and there are cost barriers.
y barreras de costo.
Sometimes there are booking delays, and availability
A veces hay retrasos en las reservas y la disponibilidad
is a problem getting interpreters.
es un problema conseguir intérpretes
Technological accessibility;
Accesibilidad tecnológica:
sometimes there are barriers,
a veces existen barreras
and sometimes people don't know what needs to be provided.
porque la gente no sabe qué debe proporcionarse.
They don't have that awareness.
Falta conciencia.
For an Australian audience,
Para una audiencia australiana,
we have the National Disability Insurance Scheme, the NDIS.
tenemos el Sistema Nacional de Seguro por Discapacidad, NDIS.
That provides some funding,
Eso proporciona cierta financiación,
even though it's limited, for Deaf people.
aunque sea limitada, para personas sordas.
The NDIS usually covers interpreting for social events
El NDIS generalmente cubre la interpretación para eventos sociales
and religious events, but not for the workplace.
y eventos religiosos, pero no para el lugar de trabajo.
Funding now is quite limited because,
La financiación ahora es bastante limitada porque,
beginning last year, in October 2024, there was a lot of cutbacks
a partir del año pasado, en octubre de 2024, hubo muchos recortes
to the funding that's provided,
a la financiación que se proporciona.
so Deaf people have to budget
Así que las personas sordas tienen que hacer un presupuesto.
the limited funding to pay for interpreters,
La financiación limitada para pagar a los intérpretes,
and they have to decide whether they would use
y tienen que decidir si la usarían
the interpreting funding for, say, a medical appointment
para interpretación en, digamos, una cita médica
or a social catch-up with family that may not sign.
o una reunión social con la familia que no sabe lengua de señas.
There are interpreter provisions
Existen disposiciones sobre interpretación
through the NDIS, but it's limited,
a través del NDIS, pero es limitado,
and there aren't enough interpreters.
y no hay suficientes intérpretes.
It's very difficult to become an interpreter.
Es muy difícil llegar a ser intérprete.
You need to learn the language and then learn
Necesitas aprender el idioma y luego aprender
how to become an interpreter between the two languages,
cómo convertirte en intérprete entre los dos idiomas,
because English and Auslan are two different languages.
porque el inglés y el Auslan son dos idiomas diferentes.
One's a visual language and one is an auditory language,
Uno es un lenguaje visual y el otro es un lenguaje auditivo,
a sequential language, so it takes time to develop
un lenguaje secuencial, así que lleva tiempo desarrollar
the skill to become an interpreter.
la habilidad de convertirse en intérprete.
Next, I wanted to mention the EAF,
A continuación, quería mencionar el EAF,
the "Employment Assistance Fund" in Australia.
el Fondo de Asistencia al Empleo en Australia.
That's provided through JobAccess,
Esto se proporciona a través de JobAccess
and it's a federally government-funded department.
y es un departamento federal financiado por el gobierno.
The EAF is for Deaf people
El EAF es para personas sordas
in the workplace or have small businesses,
en el lugar de trabajo o con pequeños negocios,
but again, there is support available, but it's limited.
pero, nuevamente, hay apoyo disponible, aunque es limitado.
The support is the provision of an interpreter and costs
El apoyo es la provisión de intérpretes y costos
for interpreters, as well as any technologies,
para interpretación, así como cualquier tecnología,
as well as video interpreting.
incluida la interpretación por video.
Also, Auslan training for staff members
Además, formación en Auslan para miembros del personal
in the workplace and Deaf cultural training,
en el lugar de trabajo y formación cultural sobre sordera,
but it can be limited.
pero puede ser limitado.
Recently, the government in Australia has increased
Recientemente, el gobierno en Australia ha aumentado
the funds to around $12,000 a year, per person,
los fondos a alrededor de $12,000 dólares al año por persona,
but you may have a professional Deaf person
pero podrías tener una persona sorda profesional
working in a business where meetings are frequent.
trabajando en un negocio donde las reuniones son frecuentes.
That money is going to run out within three or four months.
Ese dinero se agotará en tres o cuatro meses.
If you work in a lower-level position,
Si trabajas en una posición de nivel inferior,
the EAF may be able to accommodate you for up
el EAF podría ser capaz de cubrirte hasta
to a year if you only had meetings, say, monthly.
un año si solo tuvieras reuniones, digamos, mensuales.
If you had fortnightly or weekly meetings,
Si tuvieras reuniones quincenales o semanales,
then the funds wouldn't cover interpreter access,
entonces los fondos no cubrirían el acceso a intérpretes,
and they would then put it back
y luego se trasladaría
on the employer to provide the funding for interpreting.
al empleador la responsabilidad de proporcionar la financiación para la interpretación.
Some organizations do try
Algunas organizaciones lo intentan,
to double-dip using the NDIS,
realizar un doble financiamiento utilizando el NDIS,
but the NDIS is not for that purpose.
pero el NDIS no existe para ese propósito.
It's a different scheme to interpreting
Es un esquema diferente a la interpretación
and access in the workplace, so often,
y el acceso en el lugar de trabajo, por lo tanto, a menudo,
businesses need to take on that responsibility
las empresas necesitan asumir esa responsabilidad
to pay for interpreter costs.
para pagar los costos de interpretación.
Both the NDIS and the EAF are all limited
Tanto el NDIS como el EAF son limitados
in terms of funding ability,
en términos de capacidad de financiación
and it's funded by taxpayers throughout the country.
y están financiados por los contribuyentes de todo el país.
Just a reminder.
Solo un recordatorio.
To improve access in the workplace and with WordPress,
Para mejorar el acceso en el lugar de trabajo y con WordPress,
remembering that there's general principles to follow
recordar que hay principios generales a seguir
and making sure that WordPress features are Deaf-friendly,
y asegurarse de que las funciones de WordPress estén adaptadas para personas sordas.
making sure that things are clear on a screen
Asegurarse de que las cosas sean claras en pantalla
and sizes are taken into consideration,
y que los tamaños se tomen en consideración,
making sure that community
asegurándose de que la comunidad
is also involved in that design phase.
también esté involucrada en esa fase de diseño.
In Australia, often, Deaf people are asked
En Australia, a menudo se pide a las personas sordas
to give feedback on different WordPress projects
dar retroalimentación en diferentes proyectos de WordPress
or on different projects throughout the country.
o en diferentes proyectos en todo el país.
We've celebrated The Week of Deaf People recently,
Recientemente celebramos la Semana de las Personas Sordas
and often, Deaf people will come to businesses
y, a menudo, las personas sordas visitan empresas
and share their knowledge about Auslan and Deaf culture,
y comparten sus conocimientos sobre Auslan y la cultura sorda,
so that's something to consider.
así que eso es algo a tener en cuenta.
The responsibilities of businesses
Las responsabilidades de las empresas
and institutions is to provide Deaf-friendly access
y las instituciones son proporcionar acceso adaptado para personas sordas
in the WordPress space.
en el espacio de WordPress.
There are legal compliance requirements in Australia.
Existen requisitos legales de cumplimiento en Australia.
We have the Disability Discrimination Act of 1991,
Tenemos la Ley contra la Discriminación por Discapacidad de 1991,
and we also have accessibility standards to ensure
y también tenemos normas de accesibilidad para garantizar
that communication access
que el acceso a la comunicación
is designed so that it's inclusive.
esté diseñado para ser inclusivo.
Also, again, mentioning that consultation
Además, nuevamente, mencionar que la consulta
with Deaf people is important,
con las personas sordas es importante,
and also offering information in multiple formats.
y también ofrecer información en múltiples formatos.
Making sure that you have that intersectionality
Asegurarse de que se tenga esa interseccionalidad
within your consultation with Deaf people,
dentro de su consulta con personas sordas,
making sure that perhaps Indigenous Deaf people
asegurándose de que quizá personas sordas indígenas
or people of color are also included, making that available.
o también personas racializadas estén incluidas, poniéndolo a disposición.
Also, making sure that Deaf people are paid
Además, asegúrese de que a las personas sordas se les pague
for their time if they do consult with you.
por su tiempo si consultan contigo.
My experience over the last 15 years has been quite extensive,
Mi experiencia en los últimos 15 años ha sido bastante extensa,
and I've had a lot of organizations,
y he tenido muchas organizaciones,
government, as well as private, asking me to volunteer
gubernamentales, así como privadas, pidiéndome que sea voluntario
my time to provide consultancy work,
mi tiempo para brindar trabajo de consultoría,
and sometimes, they'll just pay
y a veces simplemente pagan
for your lunch or a very small remuneration.
tu almuerzo o una remuneración muy pequeña.
It's important that Deaf people
Es importante que las personas sordas
are recognized for the time that they give,
sean reconocidas por el tiempo que dan,
especially if they've got to travel
especialmente si tienen que viajar
to your office or meet with you over Zoom.
a tu oficina o reunirse contigo a través de Zoom.
Deaf people,
Las personas sordas,
I guess, can't be considered cheap labor and exploited.
no pueden considerarse mano de obra barata ni explotable.
People with disabilities generally deserve
Las personas con discapacidad generalmente merecen
to have real recognition for the skills, expertise,
tener un reconocimiento real por las habilidades y experiencia,
and effort that they bring to support your project
y el esfuerzo que aportan para apoyar su proyecto
and any activities that you might do with WordPress.
y cualquier actividad que pueda realizarse con WordPress.
In summary, just a reminder here,
En resumen, solo un recordatorio aquí:
be aware of the Disability Discrimination Act.
tener en cuenta la Ley contra la Discriminación por Discapacidad.
You can find all of that information
Puedes encontrar toda esa información
by Googling it or asking a Deaf person for more information.
buscándola en Google o preguntando a una persona sorda para obtener más información.
Making sure that when you consult
Asegurarse de que cuando se consulte
with Deaf people, you make sure that you think about
con personas sordas, se piense en
all of the different accessibility needs,
todas las diferentes necesidades de accesibilidad,
because not all services
porque no todos los servicios
might be the right skill set that you require,
tendrán el conjunto de habilidades adecuado que se requiere,
so getting that expertise from Deaf people
así que obtener esa experiencia de personas sordas
with lived experience, because they often
con experiencia vivida, porque a menudo
are the ones that know best.
son quienes mejor lo saben.
Deaf people will give you their preferences,
Las personas sordas darán sus preferencias,
especially about particular interpreters
especialmente sobre intérpretes particulares
that might be used.
que podrían utilizarse.
Not all interpreters will be suitable for all different things,
No todos los intérpretes serán adecuados para todas las situaciones,
so we need to make sure
así que debemos asegurarnos
that we incorporate the styles that are suitable
de incorporar los estilos apropiados
in the interpreting profession.
en la profesión de interpretación.
We need to make sure that Deaf people are paid for their time,
Necesitamos asegurarnos de que a las personas sordas se les pague por su tiempo,
as I mentioned before, in the design process.
como mencioné antes, en el proceso de diseño.
Making sure that fonts and the font sizes
Asegurarse de que las fuentes y los tamaños de fuente
and pictures are used, and easy English is used,
y las imágenes se utilicen, y se use un inglés sencillo,
and things are not too wordy, because it's very difficult to get
y que las cosas no sean demasiado verbosas, porque es muy difícil
the Deaf person to engage when that occurs.
que la persona sorda se involucre cuando eso ocurre.
Making sure that picture-in-picture
Asegurarse de que el formato imagen en imagen
format for Auslan interpreters
para intérpretes de Auslan
and also into spoken English from Auslan,
y también en el inglés hablado desde Auslan,
the translations are there,
las traducciones estén presentes,
and also the text translations as well,
y también traducciones en texto,
so that Deafblind interpreters
para que los intérpretes sordociegos
are able to access that information.
puedan acceder a esa información.
They may be tactile signing, which is hand-on-hand signing.
Pueden ser señas táctiles, que es firmar mano a mano.
There could be a whole list of different requirements.
Podría haber toda una lista de requisitos diferentes.
At the bottom of this slide, that is our Deaf flag,
En la parte inferior de esta diapositiva, esa es nuestra bandera de las personas sordas,
and we're very proud to have a flag that represents Deaf people
y estamos muy orgullosos de tener una bandera que representa a las personas sordas,
that was put out by the World Federation of the Deaf.
que fue establecida por la Federación Mundial de Sordos.
These are national resources now on this slide
Estos son recursos nacionales ahora en esta diapositiva
that you can perhaps have a look at later.
que quizás puedas echarles un vistazo más tarde.
These are my contact details.
Estos son mis datos de contacto.
You can contact me via text message or email,
Puedes contactarme por mensaje de texto o correo electrónico,
Facebook, or LinkedIn,
Facebook o LinkedIn,
and because this is an international audience,
y, como esta es una audiencia internacional,
don't forget to use the +61 for the mobile text messaging.
no olvides usar el +61 para la mensajería de texto móvil.
If you're wanting to learn the sign for thank you, it is this.
Si quieres aprender la seña de agradecimiento, es esta.
[signs "thank you"]
[hace la seña de "gracias"]
Thank you.
Gracias.
If you write with your right hand,
Si escribes con la mano derecha,
you use your right hand as your dominant hand.
usas tu mano derecha como mano dominante.
If you write with your left hand,
Si escribes con la mano izquierda,
it is your left hand that's your dominant hand.
es tu mano izquierda la que es dominante.
That's how we teach finger spelling.
Así es como enseñamos el deletreo manual.
One hand is dominant,
Una mano es dominante,
depending on whether you're left or right-handed.
dependiendo de si eres zurdo o diestro.
Now we'll move to the question-and-answer session.
Ahora pasaremos a la sesión de preguntas y respuestas.
Thank you all.
Gracias a todos.
Bye-bye.
Adiós.
Alicia: Okay.
Está bien.
That was absolutely mesmerizing.
Eso fue absolutamente fascinante.
Thank you so much,
Muchas gracias,
Shawn, for that presentation, and I just want to say a few things.
Shawn, por esa presentación, y solo quiero decir algunas cosas.
I don't think everyone who's here knows that there's
No creo que todos los que están aquí sepan que
a tin-can translation happening here.
aquí se está produciendo una traducción improvisada.
He's speaking Auslan,
Él está usando Auslan,
or he's actually signing Auslan while someone else is translating it
o en realidad está firmando en Auslan mientras alguien más lo traduce
to American Sign Language, while someone else is translating
al lenguaje de señas americano, mientras otra persona traduce
that to vocal
eso a voz
that we heard.
que hemos escuchado.
It was the first time in my experience that I've seen this sign language first
Es la primera vez en mi experiencia que veo primero la lengua de señas
and the voice coming second.
y la voz viene después.
I don't know if anybody got the emphasis of that,
No sé si todos captaron el énfasis de eso,
but it was very different,
pero fue muy diferente,
very unique,
muy único,
and thank you so much for sharing this,
y muchas gracias por compartirlo,
Shawn. I really appreciate it.
Shawn, lo agradezco mucho.
We do have questions.
Tenemos preguntas.
Shawn jumped on these questions, and so I'm going to read out his answers
Shawn respondió algunas de estas preguntas, y voy a leer sus respuestas
because not everyone can see the answer.
porque no todos pueden verlas.
I'm going to go ahead.
Continuaré.
The one that we all immediately had a question was when you said
La primera pregunta que todos tuvimos fue cuando dijiste
it's two-handed signing.
que es una seña a dos manos.
Right away, Amy was on this one.
Inmediatamente Amy preguntó:
I'm curious about how folks who use two-handed finger spelling adapt
"Tengo curiosidad por saber cómo las personas adaptan el deletreo manual a dos manos
when they have limb differences or an injury preventing
cuando tienen diferencias en las extremidades o una lesión que impide
the use of two hands,
el uso de ambas manos".
and the answer is really intriguing.
Y la respuesta es realmente intrigante.
It was, yes, in Australia, it is called phantom signing
Fue: "Sí, en Australia se llama seña fantasma,
or phantom one-hand signing adapted from Auslan two-hand signing.
o seña fantasma con una sola mano, adaptada del Auslan a dos manos.
Not all Auslan deaf signers
No todos los usuarios sordos de Auslan
or Auslan interpreters understand that approach unless it's taught at school
o los intérpretes de Auslan entienden ese enfoque, a menos que se enseñe en la escuela
or TAFE's vocational colleges.
o en los colegios vocacionales TAFE.
TAFE means Technical and Further Education.
TAFE significa Educación Técnica y Formación Avanzada".
Thank you for explaining that stuff, too, because I know a lot of the acronyms
Gracias por explicar eso también, porque conozco muchas siglas
in different countries.
en diferentes países.
There was more Q&A in here.
Hubo más preguntas y respuestas aquí.
How many sign languages do deaf people-- Speaker 1: Hey, Alicia?
"¿Cuántas lenguas de señas hablan las personas sordas...?"
Alicia: Yes?
Hola, ¿Alicia?
Speaker 1: Can you ask Shawn the questions?
¿Puedes hacerle las preguntas a Shawn?
It looks like he wants to respond.
Parece que quiere responder.
Alicia: Oh, okay. Do you want to add more to that, Shawn?
Ah, está bien. ¿Quieres añadir algo más, Shawn?
Shawn: I will add to that.
Agregaré algo más a eso.
Just to answer that question a little bit further,
Solo para responder a esa pregunta un poco más,
hearing and deaf people
personas oyentes y sordas
that may have cerebral palsy or other additional disabilities or needs,
que pueden tener parálisis cerebral u otras discapacidades o necesidades adicionales,
perhaps they may have had a stroke or they may have paralysis in their arm
quizás hayan tenido un derrame cerebral o puedan tener parálisis en el brazo
where they are unable to use that two-handed finger spelling.
donde no pueden utilizar el deletreo con dos manos.
What they might do is they would use their dominant hand or the hand
Lo que podrían hacer es utilizar su mano dominante
that they are still able to function with, and people would have those skills
con la que todavía pueden funcionar, y la gente desarrollaría habilidades
to be able to use that finger spelling, and just imagining
para poder usar ese deletreo manual, simplemente imaginando
that the non-dominant hand is still there.
que la mano no dominante aún está allí.
Then people may learn through TAFE, universities,
Entonces las personas pueden aprender a través de TAFE, universidades
schools,
y escuelas
just how to understand those finger spellings.
cómo entender ese deletreo dactilológico.
For example, if I was to spell the word night,
Por ejemplo, si deletreara la palabra "noche",
N-I-G-H-T, and if I look at that in the dictionary,
N-O-C-H-E, y si miro eso en el diccionario,
the sign for that is like this, where the one hand moves
la seña es así, donde una mano se mueve
horizontally down.
horizontalmente hacia abajo.
It's usually a two-handed sign, but for example,
Generalmente es una seña de dos manos, pero por ejemplo,
if I only had the one hand, I could just use the one hand
si solo tuviera una mano, podría usar una sola
to sign that, and that is quite flexible.
para hacerla, y es bastante flexible.
Another sign, for example,
Otra seña, por ejemplo,
computer, you can see that's a two-handed sign,
"computadora", puedes ver que es de dos manos,
but if you were only able to use one hand, you could still use that dominant hand
pero si solo pudieras usar una, aún podrías usar la dominante
to move, to show the parameters of that sign,
para mostrar los parámetros del signo,
such as the movement, the hand shape.
como el movimiento y la forma de la mano.
It's similar to how people who may not be able to use their voice
Es similar a cómo la gente que quizás no puede usar su voz
to pronounce all their words, but for deaf people,
para pronunciar todas sus palabras, pero para las personas sordas,
they may be able to use those lip patterns and lip cues alongside that hand
quizás puedan usar esos patrones labiales y movimientos de labios junto con la mano
that is still in dominant use.
que todavía utilizan de forma dominante.
We do call that phantom signing.
A eso lo llamamos firma fantasma.
I don't know a whole lot about that.
No sé mucho sobre eso.
I didn't grow up learning about that in school,
No crecí aprendiendo sobre ello en la escuela,
until I went to TAFE,
hasta que fui a TAFE,
which is that Tertiary and Further Education.
que es Educación Técnica y Superior.
When that happened or in college,
Fue entonces, o en la universidad,
that's when the teacher taught me about that.
cuando el profesor me enseñó sobre eso.
That was when I understood a little bit more,
Ahí fue cuando lo entendí un poco más,
but there are many young deaf people in Australia that would not know so much
pero hay muchos jóvenes sordos en Australia que no sabrían tanto
about phantom signing.
sobre la firma fantasma.
Alicia: Wow.
Vaya.
Okay.
Bueno.
I'm going to let you go for the other one too, Shawn.
Te dejaré responder la otra también, Shawn.
You had, how many sign languages do deaf people learn and use in the USA,
Tenías: “¿Cuántas lenguas de señas aprenden y usan las personas sordas en EE. UU.,
in UK, and Australia?
en el Reino Unido y en Australia?”
Shawn,
Shawn,
you answered that before, but go ahead and answer for everyone,
ya respondiste eso antes, pero adelante, responde para todos,
if you would like.
si quieres.
Shawn: Yes, certainly.
Sí, por supuesto.
Just letting you know that the World Federation for the Deaf,
Solo para avisarles que la Federación Mundial de Sordos,
so that's the WFD, the World Federation,
es decir, la WFD, la Federación Mundial,
sorry, of the Deaf,
lo siento, de Sordos,
so there are many sign languages in the world,
indica que hay muchas lenguas de señas
over 400 different sign languages that we have.
en el mundo, más de 400 lenguas de señas diferentes.
With the people
Entre las personas
who are deaf and hard of hearing, not everybody would use a sign language.
sordas o con dificultades auditivas, no todas usarían lengua de señas.
There are also deaf-blind communities who would use hand-over-hand
También existen comunidades sordociegas que usarían mano sobre mano
or tactile signing,
o señas táctiles,
and so there are many deaf people in Australia,
y hay muchas personas sordas en Australia,
New Zealand, in Europe, in England, America,
Nueva Zelanda, Europa, Inglaterra y América
who would all use different sign languages.
que usan diferentes lenguas de señas.
There isn't a universal sign language across the world.
No existe una lengua de señas universal en todo el mundo.
There are many people who believe that Auslan is the same as ASL,
Muchas personas creen que Auslan es igual que ASL,
which is American Sign Language,
la lengua de señas americana,
but no, as you can see, one of those differences,
pero no. Como puedes ver, una diferencia, por ejemplo, es “qué”.
for an example, is what.
Esta es la seña
This is a sign for what in Auslan, but in ASL,
para “qué” en Auslan, pero en ASL,
American Sign Language,
Lengua de Señas Americana,
the sign for what actually means where in Auslan.
la seña de “qué” en realidad significa “dónde” en Auslan.
The same sign
El mismo signo
means a completely different thing in the different language.
significa algo completamente diferente en otro idioma.
If we were signing,
Si estuviéramos señando,
"Where's your this?"
“¿Dónde está esto?”
sometimes we get confused as Australian people reading
a veces nos confundimos, ya que los australianos leen
that sign language to say, "Where's your what?"
esa seña como “¿Dónde está tu qué?”,
which is quite tricky.
lo cual es bastante complicado.
In Auslan, this is the sign for where, which is different
En Auslan, esta es la seña para “dónde”,
from the American sign,
diferente
which looks like the Australian sign for what,
de la seña Americana,
so that does get quite confusing.
que se parece a la Australiana para “qué”,
The audience who lives in the UK,
así que resulta bastante confuso.
there are also a bit of a funny story or a funny sign,
también hay una historia divertida
I'll keep it professional, but the sign for Coke,
sobre la seña de Coca-Cola.
C-O-K-E,
“Coca”,
in the context of a drink, is the sign for this.
en el contexto de una bebida, es esta seña,
Whereas in BSL Sign Language, deaf people could be quite offended
mientras que en BSL Lengua de Señas, las personas sordas podrían ofenderse
when they see that, because that sign would mean sex.
porque esa seña significa sexo.
There are different signs between Auslan and other sign languages,
Hay diferentes señas entre Auslan y otras lenguas de señas,
also the different hand shapes that can be considered quite rude as well.
y también diferentes configuraciones de mano pueden considerarse groseras.
That hand shape there with the middle finger raised is
Esa forma de mano con el dedo medio levantado es
the Japanese sign for brother.
la seña Japonesa de “hermano”.
Whereas in our culture and context, we would consider that handshake
Mientras que en nuestra cultura se consideraría grosero
to be quite rude if we were sticking up the middle finger.
mostrar el dedo medio.
Considering that,
Asimismo,
the different states in Australia also have some variation.
los diferentes estados en Australia también tienen variaciones.
Between Queensland, New South Wales, ACT,
Entre Queensland, Nueva Gales del Sur, ACT,
Victoria, Western Australia, South Australia,
Victoria, Australia Occidental y Australia del Sur,
we have what's called
tenemos lo que se llaman
regional dialects.
dialectos regionales.
In Queensland, the sign for hungry is this,
En Queensland, la seña de hambre es esta:
where the hands fall down from the stomach,
las manos bajan desde el estómago,
but in Melbourne and in Victoria, the sign for hungry is that,
pero en Melbourne y Victoria la seña de hambre es esta,
the thumb brushing downwards on the neck.
el pulgar rozando el cuello hacia abajo.
If a person from Melbourne goes to Brisbane for a holiday
Si una persona de Melbourne va a Brisbane de vacaciones
and they were to meet somebody from there and they signed that hungry with the thumb
y se encuentra con alguien allí y hace la seña de hambre con el pulgar
on the neck,
en el cuello,
the Queensland deaf people, or who interpret that,
las personas sordas de Queensland, o quién interpreta eso
might be quite offended because that sign is also the sign for sex.
podrían sentirse ofendidas, porque también significa sexo.
That's the sign for sex in Queensland, whereas it's the sign for hungry.
Esa es la seña de sexo en Queensland, mientras que en Victoria significa hambre.
For example, when we say Hungry Jack's in Queensland and we sign that,
Por ejemplo, cuando decimos Hungry Jack's en Queensland y hacemos esa seña,
we say, "Oh, does that mean--
decimos: “Oh, ¿eso significa…?”
are you saying Jack is sexy?"
¿Estás diciendo que Jack es sexy?
Queensland people who are signing,
Personas de Queensland que están señando,
and another example for coffee, this is the sign for coffee.
y otro ejemplo: para café, esta es la seña de café.
When you come down to Melbourne and you sign that,
Cuando bajas a Melbourne y haces esa seña,
that's actually talking about a car.
en realidad estás hablando de un coche.
It does look like when you're winding up the car,
Sí parece como si estuvieras dando arranque al coche,
so you do have to be careful when you are learning Auslan.
así que debes tener cuidado cuando aprendes Auslan.
It's better to learn the dialect that's within your state,
Es mejor aprender el dialecto que corresponde a tu estado,
but just to be aware that there are differences
pero también ser consciente de que hay diferencias
all across Australia.
en toda Australia.
I heard that in America, this sign
Escuché que en Estados Unidos esta seña…
on your heart is also quite similar to another sign for assume
sobre el corazón también es bastante similar a otra seña para asumir
or an accent.
o un acento.
I believe that within Australian cities and countries,
Creo que dentro de las ciudades Australianas y los países,
also within the Indigenous Australians.
también ocurre dentro de comunidades Indígenas Australianas.
Speaker 2: Thank you so much.
Muchas gracias.
Speaker 3: I'm so sorry.
Lo sentimos mucho.
We want to make sure we are respectful of all of our sign language interpreters.
Queremos asegurarnos de ser respetuosos con todos nuestros intérpretes de lengua de señas.
Thank you all so much for this amazing session.
Muchas gracias a todos por esta increíble sesión.
Alicia: It's amazing.
Es increíble.
Speaker 3: All right. We will see you all-
Está bien. Nos vemos a todos.
Shawn: Thank you. Thank you so much.
Gracias. Muchas gracias.
Speaker 3: -in the very next session.
—en la próxima sesión.
Thank you.
Gracias.
Alicia: Okay, thank you.
Está bien, gracias.